Greetings, my lord!
السلام عليكم يا سيدي!
My lady is in the main hall.
سيدتي في القاعة الرئيسية.
Right this way.
تفضل من هنا.
Very well.
جيد جدا.
My lady!
سيدتي!
My lord,
سيدي،
it appears the ladies
يبدو أن السيدات
have stepped into the courtyard.
دخلوا إلى الفناء.
Please sit.
تفضل بالجلوس.
I shall find them.
سأجدهم.
Aye.
فرصة.
Wanxue,
وانكسو,
there's
هناك
something I have
شيء أملكه
long wished to tell you.
كنت أتمنى أن أخبرك بذلك منذ فترة طويلة.
Go on, then.
هيا بنا إذن.
Please stay.
أرجو البقاء.
My lord,
سيدي،
my lady's right there.
سيدتي هناك.
Aunt Jinzhao,
العمة جين تشاو،
I have words
لدي كلمات
for Wanxue.
لـ وانكسيو.
I ask that you bear witness.
أطلب منكم أن تشهدوا.
The truth is...
الحقيقة هي...
My heart has long
قلبي طويل
belonged to another.
كان ملكاً لشخص آخر.
Hold your tongue!
اصمت!
You are
أنت
betrothed to Wanxue.
مخطوبة لوانكسيو.
Who is she?
من هي؟
Tell me!
أخبرني!
Chen Xuanqing,
تشن شوانكينج,
a man your age
رجل في سنك
knows the cost
يعرف التكلفة
of words.
من الكلمات.
Just tell me!
أخبرني فقط!
I won't.
أنا لن.
I'm here to
أنا هنا من أجل
give you the truth.
سأخبرك بالحقيقة.
She is real.
إنها حقيقية.
If this is too much to bear
إذا كان هذا الأمر يفوق طاقتك على التحمل
for you,
لك،
we should end it.
يجب أن نضع حداً لذلك.
Enough!
كافٍ!
Do you even
هل أنت حتى
hear yourself?
هل تسمع نفسك؟
As though she
كما لو أنها
owes you that mercy!
أنا مدين لك بهذه الرحمة!
If another woman
إذا كانت امرأة أخرى
held your heart,
أمسكت بقلبك،
you had no right to take her hand.
لم يكن لك الحق في الإمساك بيدها.
Wanxue,
وانكسو,
come,
يأتي،
the Chens
عائلة تشين
owe you a reckoning.
سأحاسبك.
I'll see to it.
سأحرص على ذلك.
No.
لا.
If your heart
إذا كان قلبك
belongs to another,
ينتمي إلى شخص آخر،
why did you ask for my hand?
لماذا طلبت يدي؟
Was it after you
هل كان ذلك بعدك؟
- proposed that you... - I fell for her...
- اقترحت عليكِ... - لقد وقعت في حبها...
before the proposal.
قبل تقديم الاقتراح.
Then why...
إذن لماذا...
Because she is beyond my reach.
لأنها بعيدة المنال.
She always
هي دائماً
has been.
كان.
She always will be.
ستظل كذلك دائماً.
Has reason left you entirely?
هل فقدتَ عقلك تماماً؟
I hear you.
أفهمك.
But I'm not breaking this off.
لكنني لن أنهي هذا الأمر.
Let her live in your heart.
دعها تعيش في قلبك.
I'll live in your home.
سأسكن في منزلك.
Why'd you carry that weight?
لماذا تحملت هذا الوزن؟
Because
لأن
I've loved you my whole life.
لقد أحببتك طوال حياتي.
The day my father told me
اليوم الذي أخبرني فيه والدي
I was to be yours...
كان من المفترض أن أكون لك...
that was the first day I truly hoped.
كان ذلك أول يوم شعرت فيه بالأمل حقاً.
Every time my stepmother was cruel,
في كل مرة كانت زوجة أبي قاسية،
every time I nearly broke,
في كل مرة كنت على وشك الانهيار،
I'd say to myself:
أقول لنفسي:
hold on, Wanxue.
انتظري يا وانكسيو.
He's waiting for you.
إنه ينتظرك.
You're
أنت
almost there.
اقتربنا من النهاية.
I won't give this up!
لن أتخلى عن هذا!
I won't! Never!
لن أفعل! أبداً!
My dear,
عزيزي،
listen...
يستمع...
Very well.
جيد جدا.
If that is your wish,
إذا كانت هذه رغبتك،
then
ثم
nothing changes.
لا شيء يتغير.
Aunt Jinzhao,
العمة جين تشاو،
what happened here today,
ما حدث هنا اليوم،
let it stay here.
دعه يبقى هنا.
Some matters
بعض الأمور
are wiser left undisturbed.
من الحكمة تركها دون إزعاج.
Surely you agree.
بالتأكيد أنت توافق.
Wanxue
وانكسو
has chosen.
لقد اختار.
I will honor that.
سأحترم ذلك.
But she deserves
لكنها تستحق
to be chosen in return.
ليتم اختيارهم في المقابل.
My lord...
يا سيدي...
I...
أنا...
You saw nothing today.
لم ترَ شيئاً اليوم.
Nothing.
لا شئ.
Yes, my lord.
نعم يا سيدي.
My lord,
سيدي،
perhaps...
ربما...
I
أنا
should look into...
ينبغي النظر في...
No,
لا،
there's nothing to look into.
لا يوجد ما يستدعي البحث.
Jinzhao keeps nothing from me.
لا يخفي جينزهاو عني شيئاً.
I'll hear it from her.
سأسمع ذلك منها.
Yes, my lord.
نعم يا سيدي.
See to the men.
اهتم بالرجال.
My lady.
سيدتي.
What brings you here?
ما الذي أتى بك إلى هنا؟
Official business
أعمال رسمية
brought me nearby.
أحضرني إلى مكان قريب.
Couldn't pass without stopping,
لم أستطع المرور دون التوقف،
congratulations on
تهانينا
the new chapter.
الفصل الجديد.
Perfect timing.
توقيت مثالي.
I was just thinking of leaving.
كنت أفكر في المغادرة.
Then
ثم
let's go home.
هيا بنا إلى المنزل.
I still have things to attend to.
لا يزال لديّ بعض الأمور التي يجب عليّ القيام بها.
Go on inside.
ادخل إلى الداخل.
Fine.
بخير.
I thought he was a decent man.
كنت أظن أنه رجل طيب.
I gave him that much.
أعطيته هذا القدر.
How wrong I was.
كم كنت مخطئاً.
My lady,
سيدتي،
does my lord
يا سيدي
need to know this?
هل تحتاج إلى معرفة هذا؟
He does.
نعم، يفعل.
But I know his temper.
لكنني أعرف طبعه.
The moment this comes to light,
في اللحظة التي يتضح فيها هذا الأمر،
he'll have the betrothal
سيُعقد له حفل الخطوبة
dissolved by morning.
تذوب بحلول الصباح.
And Wanxue's
ووانكسو
made her choice and
اتخذت قرارها و
nothing will move her from it.
لن يثنيها شيء عن ذلك.
This is what we do.
هذا ما نفعله.
Pass the word:
انشر الخبر:
Xuanqing does not set foot
لم تطأ شوانكينغ قدمها
in this courtyard.
في هذه الساحة.
Not without
ليس بسبب
my leave.
إجازتي.
And I want
وأريد
eyes on him.
الأنظار عليه.
Morning greetings,
تحية صباحية،
meals,
وجبات الطعام،
wherever he shows up,
أينما يظهر،
I disappear.
أختفي.
Keep us apart.
أبقونا بعيدين عن بعضنا.
Yes, my lady.
نعم يا سيدتي.
Bamboo shoots here,
براعم الخيزران هنا،
Madam will want them near.
سترغب السيدة في وجودهم بالقرب منها.
Right here.
هنا بالضبط.
Yes, my lady.
نعم يا سيدتي.
Now see what's left
والآن انظر ماذا تبقى
in the kitchen,
في المطبخ،
and bring it all out.
وأخرج كل شيء.
My lady.
سيدتي.
Stop dawdling.
توقف عن التباطؤ.
I want this table set properly.
أريد أن يتم تجهيز هذه الطاولة بشكل صحيح.
Darling,
محبوب،
keeping busy
إشغال النفس
these days?
في هذه الأيام؟
Somewhat,
إلى حد ما،
Grandmother.
جدة.
The academy
الأكاديمية
is compiling the imperial codex.
يقوم بتجميع المخطوطة الإمبراطورية.
Busier than before,
أكثر ازدحاماً من ذي قبل،
but
لكن
manageable.
يمكن إدارتها.
Good.
جيد.
Mrs. Yu paid us a visit
قامت السيدة يو بزيارتنا
the other day
في اليوم الآخر
and brought up your wedding.
وأثار موضوع زفافك.
Madam,
سيدتي،
my lady
سيدتي
tired herself out today.
أرهقت نفسها اليوم.
She's feeling unwell.
إنها تشعر بتوعك.
She sends her apologies for this evening.
إنها تعتذر عما حدث هذا المساء.
If she's unwell,
إذا كانت مريضة،
she should rest.
ينبغي عليها أن تستريح.
She can skip morning greetings as well.
يمكنها أيضاً أن تتخطى تحية الصباح.
Yes, Madam.
نعم سيدتي.
Eat.
يأكل.
What hour is it?
كم الساعة؟
Do you have to leave already?
هل يجب عليك المغادرة الآن؟
Not yet.
ليس بعد.
You've been run ragged lately.
لقد كنت مرهقاً للغاية مؤخراً.
Aye.
فرصة.
It's flood season.
إنه موسم الفيضانات.
Every waterway needs reinforcing,
كل ممر مائي يحتاج إلى تدعيم،
and every local official
وكل مسؤول محلي
has come begging for funds.
لقد جاء يتوسل للحصول على الأموال.
You get
ستحصل
no sleep as it is.
لا نوم أصلاً.
Honestly,
بصدق،
just stay at the office
ابقَ في المكتب
and spare yourself the ride.
ووفر على نفسك عناء الرحلة.
What?
ماذا؟
What's with
ما الذي يحدث؟
the long face?
الوجه العابس؟
You'd have me sleep at the office.
تريدني أن أنام في المكتب.
You think I want you gone?
أتظن أنني أريدك أن ترحل؟
I'd keep you here
سأبقيك هنا
every day if I could.
كل يوم لو أمكنني ذلك.
We haven't had
لم نشهد
a single moment
لحظة واحدة
to ourselves
لأنفسنا
since the wedding.
منذ الزفاف.
Your weariness pains my heart.
يؤلمني إرهاقك.
Then let us take that moment now.
فلنغتنم تلك اللحظة الآن.
[Gallivanting past curfew…]
[التجول بعد حظر التجول…]
[Pray, what does the law prescribe?]
[يا إلهي، ماذا ينص عليه القانون؟]
[His Majesty made an exception.]
[لقد استثنى جلالته هذه الحالة.]
[Such favor bestowed upon my lord!]
[يا له من فضل عظيم مُنح لسيدي!]
[Still harboring a grudge?]
[هل ما زلت تحمل ضغينة؟]
[Grudge?]
[ضغينة؟]
[You ought to be held to account.]
[يجب محاسبتك.]
[For what offense?]
[ما هي التهمة؟]
[Rousing me before daybreak,]
[إيقاظي قبل الفجر،]
[only to sulk at me.]
[فقط ليتجهم عليّ.]
[Still stewing, hm?]
[ما زلتَ تغلي غضباً، أليس كذلك؟]
[Yes,]
[نعم،]
[for quite a bit longer.]
[لفترة أطول بكثير.]
[I await your verdict]
[أنتظر حكمكم]
[with pleasure.]
[بكل سرور.]
[Look at her.]
[انظر إليها.]
[Not a shadow on her face.]
[لا ظل على وجهها.]
[Whatever she hides within,]
[مهما كان ما تخفيه في داخلها،]
[she has made peace with it.]
[لقد تصالحت مع الأمر.]
[So let her keep it.]
[لذا دعها تحتفظ به.]
My lady!
سيدتي!
My lady,
سيدتي،
where did you
أين ذهبت؟
disappear to?
إلى أين تختفي؟
I knocked for an age,
طرقت الباب لوقت طويل،
nothing.
لا شئ.
I opened the door,
فتحت الباب،
empty.
فارغ.
You nearly stilled my heart.
كادت أن تُسكت قلبي.
My lord took me out...
أخذني سيدي إلى الخارج...
At that hour?
في تلك الساعة؟
My lord and his wild notions.
سيدي وأفكاره الجامحة.
Count his wild notions
أحصِ أفكاره الجامحة
and you'll be occupied
وستكون مشغولاً
all day.
طوال اليوم.
My lady,
سيدتي،
HE...
هو...
left this morning.
غادرت هذا الصباح.
Come then.
هيا بنا إذن.
Let's greet Madam.
فلنرحب بالسيدة.
She went straight
ذهبت مباشرة
to Grandmother
إلى الجدة
the moment I walked out?
لحظة خروجي؟
Yes,
نعم،
Master...
يتقن...
There's more.
وهناك المزيد.
Madam has passed
توفيت السيدة
your betrothal arrangements
ترتيبات خطوبتك
to Lady Jinzhao.
للسيدة جينتشاو.
What?
ماذا؟
Hasn't this always
أليس هذا هو الحال دائماً؟
fallen to Lady Xianlan?
هل سقطت في يد السيدة شيانلان؟
Why's she meddling in it now?
لماذا تتدخل في الأمر الآن؟
I was at a loss too.
كنتُ في حيرة من أمري أيضاً.
Word is
الكلمة هي
she asked for it herself.
لقد طلبت ذلك بنفسها.
Of course she did.
بالطبع فعلت.
I'd say the same.
وأنا أقول الشيء نفسه.
Master,
يتقن،
she wants walls between you,
إنها تريد جدراناً تفصل بينكما،
high ones.
عالية.
You should build some of your own.
ينبغي عليك بناء بعضها بنفسك.
Once Lady Yu enters this house,
بمجرد دخول السيدة يو إلى هذا المنزل،
one wrong step and it all falls apart.
خطوة خاطئة واحدة، وسينهار كل شيء.
Gu Jinzhao...
قو جينزهاو ...
Master,
يتقن،
where are you going...
إلى أين أنت ذاهب...
Not another step.
لا خطوة أخرى.
If it's Lord Chen you seek,
إذا كنت تبحث عن اللورد تشين،
he's in the study.
إنه في غرفة الدراسة.
These are the lady's quarters.
هذه هي غرف السيدات.
It would not
لن يحدث ذلك
be proper.
كن لائقاً.
I wish to consult Aunt
أرغب في استشارة عمتي
on certain matters.
في بعض الأمور.
With your scholarly eminence,
مع صاحب السمو العلمي،
what could you
ماذا يمكنك أن تفعل؟
possibly need to consult her about?
ربما نحتاج إلى استشارتها بشأن هذا الأمر؟
She has buried herself
لقد دفنت نفسها
in your betrothal
في خطوبتك
every single day.
كل يوم.
She's not receiving visitors.
إنها لا تستقبل زواراً.
I'll have to ask you to leave.
سأضطر لطلب مغادرتك.
Very well.
جيد جدا.
Very well...
جيد جدا...
Five...
خمسة...
Six...
ستة...
Why is Prince Ningan
لماذا الأمير نينغان
still sitting on our money?
ما زالوا يحتفظون بأموالنا؟
We've sent word three times.
لقد أرسلنا الخبر ثلاث مرات.
The truth is,
الحقيقة هي،
there's nothing left.
لم يتبق شيء.
The whole household
جميع أفراد الأسرة
is at each other's throats
يتشاجرون بشدة
over whatever scraps remain.
على ما تبقى من الفتات.
And the prince spends
وينفق الأمير
faster than he earns.
أسرع مما يكسب.
In my humble opinion,
في رأيي المتواضع،
they won't be
لن يكونوا
paying us back any time soon.
هل سيسددون لنا المبلغ في أي وقت قريب؟
That said...
مع ذلك...
it's still a prince's house.
لا يزال منزل أمير.
A name like that doesn't lose
اسم كهذا لا يخسر
all its value at once.
كل قيمتها دفعة واحدة.
What are you suggesting?
ماذا تقترح؟
Lady Chen
السيدة تشين
was being rude
كان وقحاً
to you.
لك.
I've been
لقد كنت
thinking of a way
التفكير في طريقة
to make it sting her back.
لكي تؤلمها في ظهرها.
How would you make that happen?
كيف ستجعل ذلك يحدث؟
The lord has returned.
لقد عاد الرب.
What are you two
ما أنتما الاثنان؟
plotting over here?
هل تُدبّرون ​​مكائد هنا؟
My lord.
سيدي.
Plotting against Lord Chen.
التآمر ضد اللورد تشين.
Now that's something
هذا شيءٌ مميز.
worth plotting!
يستحق التخطيط!
By all means, carry on.
بكل تأكيد، استمر.
Go on.
هيا.
It's opening day.
إنه يوم الافتتاح.
Why come fetch me?
لماذا تأتي لأخذي؟
You could've just waited there.
كان بإمكانك الانتظار هناك فحسب.
Ah,
أوه،
Lian's wedding
حفل زفاف ليان
to Yao Wenxiu draws near.
اقترب موعد وصول ياو وينشيو.
Will you arrive the night before,
هل ستصل في الليلة السابقة؟
or on the morning itself?
أم في الصباح نفسه؟
The morning.
الصباح.
My presence
وجودي
would bring them no joy.
لن يجلب لهم ذلك أي فرح.
Jinzhao,
جينتشاو،
I must ask a favor of you.
لا بد لي من أن أطلب منك معروفاً.
Go on.
هيا.
The Mus wish to…
يرغب متحف الموسيقى في...
send a formal proposal.
أرسل اقتراحًا رسميًا.
Pardon?
عفو؟
Speak up.
تكلم بصراحة.
They want to send the betrothal gifts!
يريدون إرسال هدايا الخطوبة!
Only… not at Daxin.
لكن ليس في داكسين.
Could they come to
هل يمكنهم القدوم إلى
the Chen estate instead?
هل تقصد عقارات تشين بدلاً من ذلك؟
Well, well,
حسناً، حسناً،
so he isn't
إذن فهو ليس كذلك
so dull-witted as before?
هل ما زال غبياً كما كان من قبل؟
He improves
يتحسن
upon
على
acquaintance.
معرفة.
Does he now?
هل يفعل ذلك الآن؟
Is Wanxue
هل وانشيو
also soon to be blessed?
هل سيحظى هو الآخر بالبركة قريباً؟
She is.
هي كذلك.
We'll set a date
سنحدد موعداً
with the Yu family shortly,
مع عائلة يو قريباً،
most likely
على الأرجح
still this year.
ولا يزال هذا العام.
My ladies,
سيداتي،
Prince Ningan's men
رجال الأمير نينغان
have besieged
حاصروا
the whole place!
المكان بأكمله!
Mr. Luo is holding them off outside!
السيد لو يصدّهم في الخارج!
I've never
لم يسبق لي أن
crossed paths with him.
تقاطعت طرقنا معه.
Go with
اختر مع
Mr. Ping,
السيد بينغ،
find out what this is.
اكتشف ما هذا.
I shall keep close
سأبقى قريباً
and watch.
وشاهد.
Right.
يمين.
We keep a clean record, my lord.
نحافظ على سجل نظيف يا سيدي.
Taxes paid on time,
دفع الضرائب في الوقت المحدد،
trade honest and aboveboard.
مارس التجارة بنزاهة وشفافية.
There must be some misunderstanding.
لا بد من وجود سوء فهم ما.
My lady!
سيدتي!
Mr. Ping.
السيد بينغ.
This is Lord Lai,
هذا هو اللورد لاي،
steward to His Highness
وكيل صاحب السمو
Prince Ningan.
الأمير نينغان.
Allow me
اسمح لي
to present Lady Gu Lan,
لتقديم السيدة غو لان،
who owns
من يملك
this restaurant.
هذا المطعم.
Greetings, my lord.
السلام عليكم يا سيدي.
Lady Gu Lan?
السيدة غو لان؟
How curious.
يا للعجب!
We were told the proprietress
قيل لنا إن صاحبة المحل
is Lady Chen,
هي السيدة تشين،
wife of Lord Chen Yanyun.
زوجة اللورد تشين يانيون.
So you are… what, exactly?
إذن أنت... ماذا بالضبط؟
Lady Chen is my sister.
السيدة تشين هي أختي.
I manage this establishment
أدير هذه المؤسسة
on her behalf,
نيابة عنها،
my lord.
سيدي.
Fine then.
حسناً إذاً.
A simple matter.
مسألة بسيطة.
We have a performer
لدينا فنان
in our employ,
في خدمتنا،
Xia Xiaohan.
شيا شياوهان.
A gifted talent on the stage,
موهبة فذة على المسرح،
sharp-witted
ذكي
and pleasing to the eye,
ومبهجة للعين،
well-favored by His Highness.
يحظى بتقدير كبير من صاحب السمو.
Not long ago,
منذ وقت ليس ببعيد،
he disappeared
اختفى
without a word to anyone.
دون أن ينبس ببنت شفة لأحد.
I had inquiries made,
لقد أجريت استفسارات،
and every trail
وكل مسار
leads to
يؤدي إلى
your door.
بابك.
Deliver him to me,
سلمه إليّ،
my lady.
سيدتي.
My patience wears thin.
لقد نفد صبري.
Is not Xia Xiaohan a man?
أليس شيا شياوهان رجلاً؟
They keep a man hidden within?
هل يخفون رجلاً في الداخل؟
What is happening?
ما الذي يحدث؟
My lord.
سيدي.
We serve women only.
نحن نخدم النساء فقط.
Every servant,
كل خادم،
every soul on the staff,
كل فرد من أفراد الطاقم،
a woman.
امرأة.
The man you seek
الرجل الذي تبحث عنه
could not be concealed here.
لا يمكن إخفاؤها هنا.
I fear you've been led astray.
أخشى أنك قد ضللتَ الطريق.
My lady,
سيدتي،
are you really prepared
هل أنت مستعد حقاً؟
to stand against His Highness?
أن يقف في وجه سموه؟
I wouldn't dare.
لن أجرؤ على ذلك.
I only find it curious,
أجد الأمر غريباً فحسب.
today of all days, our first day open,
اليوم بالذات، يوم افتتاحنا الأول،
and you arrive with men
وتأتي مع رجال
to surround the place.
ليحيط بالمكان.
That is a remarkable coincidence.
That is a remarkable coincidence.
I had no knowledge
I had no knowledge
of your opening.
of your opening.
I serve only His Highness' command.
I serve only His Highness' command.
Give me the man,
Give me the man,
or
or
this stops being a conversation.
this stops being a conversation.
Men,
Men,
search the premises.
search the premises.
Hold,
Hold,
my lord.
my lord.
Put aside my sister's marriage
Put aside my sister's marriage
to Lord Chen.
to Lord Chen.
Your men storm my premises
Your men storm my premises
on our opening day.
on our opening day.
If word of this spreads,
If word of this spreads,
our reputation will be ruined.
our reputation will be ruined.
Find him, and I shall
Find him, and I shall
go with you gladly,
go with you gladly,
without a word of protest.
without a word of protest.
But if he isn't here,
But if he isn't here,
His Highness
His Highness
owes us
owes us
a full reckoning.
a full reckoning.
Every loss
Every loss
we suffer today
we suffer today
shall be laid at his feet.
shall be laid at his feet.
These good people are my witnesses.
These good people are my witnesses.
Do we have an accord,
Do we have an accord,
my lord?
my lord?
We have orders from above!
We have orders from above!
Step aside!
Step aside!
Clear the street.
Clear the street.
Official business.
Official business.
Move aside or be arrested!
Move aside or be arrested!
We have orders to search
We have orders to search
these premises for a fugitive!
these premises for a fugitive!
Move!
يتحرك!
Jinzhao,
Jinzhao,
the magistrate's men are upon us.
the magistrate's men are upon us.
Shall we send word to Lord Chen?
Shall we send word to Lord Chen?
My lady.
My lady.
Mr. Ping.
Mr. Ping.
Spare no coin,
Spare no coin,
get the leader
get the leader
into a suite.
into a suite.
I would have words with him.
I would have words with him.
My lady.
My lady.
Sir,
سيد،
right this way.
right this way.
Leave us.
Leave us.
At once.
At once.
My lady extends such courtesy,
My lady extends such courtesy,
it is only right
it is only right
that I return it.
that I return it.
My knowledge of the matter
My knowledge of the matter
is shallow at best.
is shallow at best.
Yet
Yet
one thought lingers:
one thought lingers:
Has your mistress
Has your mistress
recently made an enemy,
recently made an enemy,
one with power
one with power
enough to move against
enough to move against
a lady of her status?
a lady of her status?
Such enemies aren't common.
Such enemies aren't common.
Mr. Ping.
Mr. Ping.
Forgive me,
Forgive me,
duty calls.
duty calls.
Good day!
Good day!
Once you've weathered
Once you've weathered
enough storms,
enough storms,
you stop flinching at rain.
you stop flinching at rain.
My love!
My love!
Why are you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
Where else would I be?
Where else would I be?
Chen Yi told me
Chen Yi told me
everything.
everything.
I'm coming with you
I'm coming with you
to the magistrate.
to the magistrate.
It won't be necessary.
It won't be necessary.
I know what this is,
I know what this is,
and the magistrate
and the magistrate
isn't where the problem started.
isn't where the problem started.
Return to
Return to
your work.
your work.
Do not trouble yourself.
Do not trouble yourself.
That is not
That is not
how this works.
how this works.
You've
You've
weathered worse in business.
weathered worse in business.
But when
But when
it involves a prince
it involves a prince
and the magistrates,
and the magistrates,
that's where I step in.
that's where I step in.
Ease your mind.
Ease your mind.
I've handled men
I've handled men
with seals
with seals
on my own.
on my own.
More than once!
More than once!
And if I
And if I
start letting your name
start letting your name
open doors for me,
open doors for me,
I'm not
I'm not
a merchant anymore.
a merchant anymore.
I'll be your liability.
I'll be your liability.
A single whisper of this in the right ear
A single whisper of this in the right ear
could bring you ruin.
could bring you ruin.
No need
No need
to shoulder this alone.
to shoulder this alone.
Yes, my love.
Yes, my love.
Go,
Go,
let nothing stop you.
let nothing stop you.
I shall not be long.
I shall not be long.
My lord,
My lord,
this is
this is
unconscionable!
unconscionable!
They have truly moved against my lady!
They have truly moved against my lady!
A man of
A man of
Zheng Xiaoyou's standing…
Zheng Xiaoyou's standing…
reduced to running errands
reduced to running errands
for Wang Xuanfan?
for Wang Xuanfan?
So be it.
So be it.
He's the one
He's the one
I start with!
I start with!
My lord,
My lord,
I must excuse myself.
I must excuse myself.
My wife opened her establishment today,
My wife opened her establishment today,
yet someone has moved against her.
yet someone has moved against her.
The authorities have sealed the doors.
The authorities have sealed the doors.
Who would dare?
Who would dare?
Have the authorities
Have the authorities
lost all sense of honor?
lost all sense of honor?
My lord,
My lord,
I wonder the same.
I wonder the same.
Whoever is behind this
Whoever is behind this
fears no reprisal.
fears no reprisal.
Someone high in power
Someone high in power
must be holding their leash.
must be holding their leash.
But things
But things
have a way of coming to light.
have a way of coming to light.
And the man pulling the strings...
And the man pulling the strings...
Why are you looking at me?
Why are you looking at me?
Why do you ask, my lord?
Why do you ask, my lord?
What a curious man.
What a curious man.
His wife
His wife
courted disaster all on her own.
courted disaster all on her own.
What has that to do with me?
What has that to do with me?
Yanyun didn't rise to
Yanyun didn't rise to
where he stands
حيث يقف
so his wife could give the city
حتى تتمكن زوجته من إعطاء المدينة
something to laugh about.
شيء يدعو للضحك.
Hear me,
اسمعني،
for his honor's sake,
من أجل شرفه،
let the restaurant go.
دع المطعم يرحل.
Let all of
دع كل
your shops go.
ستغلق متاجركم.
No coin you earn
لا توجد عملات معدنية تكسبها
is worth the cost.
يستحق التكلفة.
You're wise, Mother.
أنتِ حكيمة يا أمي.
I had thought the very same.
كنت أفكر بنفس الطريقة تماماً.
Then you're both wrong.
إذن كلاكما مخطئ.
Mother.
الأم.
My, you're home rather early.
يا إلهي، لقد عدت إلى المنزل مبكراً جداً.
I heard
سمعت
what happened,
ماذا حدث،
so I came straight back.
لذا عدت مباشرة.
Not a single shop
ولا يوجد متجر واحد
shall close.
سيتم إغلاقها.
If anything, you build them grander.
بل على العكس، يمكنك بناءها بشكل أكثر فخامة.
My lord...
يا سيدي...
The whole city is gossiping.
المدينة بأكملها تتحدث عن الآخرين.
It will ruin your reputation.
سيدمر ذلك سمعتك.
Mother,
الأم،
the true shame lies
يكمن العار الحقيقي في
not in our businesses,
ليس في أعمالنا،
but in those who scheme
لكن في أولئك الذين يدبرون المكائد
to humiliate
لإذلال
my wife.
زوجتي.
Should Jinzhao
ينبغي جينتشاو
surrender now,
استسلم الآن،
others will say
سيقول آخرون
I cowered before them.
انحنيت أمامهم خوفاً.
That is the greatest dishonor of all!
هذا هو أعظم عار على الإطلاق!
Fair point...
كلامك صحيح...
Married to me all this time
متزوجة مني طوال هذا الوقت
and still staring like it's the first day.
وما زال يحدق كما لو كان اليوم الأول.
You absolutely love it.
ستحبه بالتأكيد.
My oh-so-proper husband!
زوجي المثالي!
What can I say.
ماذا عساي أن أقول؟
I've always been good at it.
لطالما كنتُ بارعاً في ذلك.
Chen Yi,
تشين يي,
tell my lady
أخبر سيدتي
what you found.
ما وجدته.
Yes,
نعم،
my lady,
سيدتي،
Prince Ningan
الأمير نينغان
did lose a performer,
لقد خسرنا فناناً،
- though that was... - My lady!
- مع أن ذلك كان... - سيدتي!
My lord.
سيدي.
I have it!
لقد حصلت عليه!
Well?
حسنًا؟
You were right, my lady.
كنتِ على حق يا سيدتي.
The one pulling the strings
الشخص الذي يحرك الخيوط
is Lady Wang.
هي السيدة وانغ.
I tailed Lord Lai to
تتبعت اللورد لاي إلى
Prince Ningan's estate.
ممتلكات الأمير نينغان.
A maid of
خادمة
Lady Wang's
ليدي وانغ
arrived soon after.
وصلوا بعد ذلك بوقت قصير.
Lord Lai left in haste shortly after,
غادر اللورد لاي على عجل بعد ذلك بوقت قصير.
so I kept on his trail.
لذلك واصلتُ تتبع أثره.
He went to
ذهب إلى
a pawnshop.
محل رهن.
I paid someone to find out
دفعت لشخص ما ليكتشف ذلك.
what he redeemed.
ما أنقذه.
It was a Gallowspass.
كان ذلك بمثابة عبور للمشنقة.
A Gallowspass?
ممر المشنقة؟
It was bestowed by His Late Majesty.
لقد منحها جلالة الملك الراحل.
That man has no idea
ذلك الرجل ليس لديه أدنى فكرة
how close he is to the edge.
كم هو قريب من الحافة.
I also discovered...
اكتشفت أيضاً...
Now it all
الآن كل شيء
falls into place.
الأمور تسير على ما يرام.
A royal doesn't
لا يفعل أحد أفراد العائلة المالكة
become someone's puppet
يصبح دمية في يد شخص ما
just over
بعد قليل
mere debts.
مجرد ديون.
To pawn the Gallowspass...
لرهن ممر المشنقة...
That's desperation.
هذا يأس.
If Lady Wang
إذا كانت السيدة وانغ
offered to
عرض على
forgive his debts
سامح ديونه
and lend him enough
وأقرضه ما يكفي
to buy it back,
لشرائها مرة أخرى،
he'd have
كان سيملك
had no choice
لم يكن أمامنا خيار
but to do her bidding.
لكن لتنفيذ أوامرها.
So
لذا
the prince was
كان الأمير
in her pocket too.
وفي جيبها أيضاً.
You know she's been
أنت تعلم أنها كانت
running loans?
هل تدير قروضًا؟
How do you know about it?
كيف عرفت بذلك؟
She saw fit to embarrass me
رأت أنه من المناسب أن تحرجني
at the tea party.
في حفلة الشاي.
So I made some inquiries
لذلك قمت ببعض الاستفسارات
into her affairs...
في شؤونها الخاصة...
It appears
يبدو
she's been
لقد كانت
extending loans
تمديد القروض
at truly
حقًا
extortionate rates.
أسعار باهظة للغاية.
My lord, I...
سيدي، أنا...
The prince is
الأمير هو
twenty thousand taels in her debt.
كانت مدينة لها بعشرين ألف تيل.
The interest alone buried him.
لقد قضى عليه الاهتمام وحده.
He couldn't pay,
لم يستطع الدفع،
and she had the Gallowspass
وكان لديها ممر المشنقة
to hold against him.
أن يُحاسب عليه.
So he had to bend to her will.
لذلك كان عليه أن يخضع لإرادتها.
And since
ومنذ ذلك الحين
I was the one who exposed
أنا من كشف الأمر
her theft of the tribute goods,
سرقتها لبضائع الجزية،
she used him to
لقد استغلته لـ
come after me.
تعالوا ورائي.
That is precisely
هذا هو بالضبط
what I uncovered,
ما اكتشفته،
my lady.
سيدتي.
She's a woman of rank,
إنها امرأة ذات مكانة،
and yet she runs illegal loans,
ومع ذلك فهي تدير قروضاً غير قانونية.
using debt
استخدام الديون
to bend royalty to her will.
لإخضاع العائلة المالكة لإرادتها.
Unbelievable.
لا يصدق.
I'll gather allies and
سأجمع الحلفاء و
have Wang Xuanfan impeached.
يجب عزل وانغ شوانفان.
To what end, exactly?
ولأي غاية تحديداً؟
What end
أي نهاية
do you have in mind?
ما الذي يدور في ذهنك؟
If we can't
إذا لم نتمكن
finish this in one move,
أنهِ هذا في خطوة واحدة،
hold off.
صد.
Try my way
جرب طريقتي
first.
أولاً.
And what is that?
وما هو ذلك؟
A woman's way.
طريقة المرأة.
What a remarkable woman.
يا لها من امرأة رائعة.
I stand guilty.
أعترف بالذنب.
Qingpu.
تشينغبو.
My lord,
سيدي،
I have to say,
لا بد لي من القول،
I never thought my lady
لم أتخيل أبداً سيدتي
could move that fast,
بإمكانها التحرك بهذه السرعة،
or dig that deep.
أو احفر إلى هذا العمق.
Which means
وهذا يعني
every coin you spent
كل قرش أنفقته
buying information was wasted.
تم إهدار معلومات الشراء.
My lord.
سيدي.
I have word on the winter garments
لدي معلومات بخصوص الملابس الشتوية
for the garrison troops.
لقوات الحامية.
The inspectors
المفتشون
found that half of the coats
ووجد أن نصف المعاطف
bound for the border
متجهة نحو الحدود
were packed
كانت ممتلئة
with rotten cotton.
بقطن فاسد.
The trouble is,
المشكلة هي،
the supplier responsible is the Dais.
المورد المسؤول هو المنصة.
Lady Fu's own kin.
أقارب السيدة فو أنفسهم.
The inspectors are cornered,
المفتشون محاصرون،
couldn't bring it
لم يستطع إحضاره
to their superiors,
إلى رؤسائهم،
couldn't let those coats
لم أستطع ترك تلك المعاطف
reach the troops.
الوصول إلى القوات.
They're stuck.
إنهم عالقون.
Chen Yi,
تشين يي,
pass this
مرر هذا
to Qingpu.
إلى تشينغبو.
But
لكن
it doesn't come from me.
هذا لا يصدر مني.
Yes, my lord.
نعم يا سيدي.
Mr. Jiang...
السيد جيانغ...
what does any of this
ما علاقة كل هذا؟
have to do with the lady?
هل له علاقة بالسيدة؟
Nothing.
لا شئ.
But if she
لكن إذا كانت
finds a way to resolve it,
يجد طريقة لحلها،
she'll have done
ستكون قد أنجزت
Lady Fu a considerable favor.
السيدة فو تُقدّم معروفاً كبيراً.
That's no small thing.
هذا ليس بالأمر الهين.
The one thing
الشيء الوحيد
that can't happen
هذا لا يمكن أن يحدث
is my lady realizing
هل تدرك سيدتي ذلك؟
my lord is behind this.
سيدي وراء هذا.
But...
لكن...
why all the secrecy?
لماذا كل هذا التكتم؟
Even if I explained,
حتى لو شرحت،
you'd never grasp it.
لن تفهم ذلك أبداً.
Since the scandal broke,
منذ اندلاع الفضيحة،
her shop's been on every tongue in town.
أصبح متجرها حديث الساعة في المدينة.
"For women only," they say.
يقولون: "للنساء فقط".
Heaven knows
يعلم الله
what filth goes on inside.
يا له من قذارة تحدث في الداخل.
See, that's why I keep you around.
لهذا السبب أبقيك بجانبي.
These silks are exquisite,
هذه الأقمشة الحريرية رائعة،
they're yours.
إنها ملكك.
I'm grateful, my lady!
أنا ممتن يا سيدتي!
I never tried to hide this.
لم أحاول إخفاء هذا الأمر أبداً.
She knows it was my doing,
هي تعلم أن ذلك كان من فعلي،
I'd wager my best pearls on it.
أراهن على ذلك بأفضل ما أملك من لآلئ.
But what can she do?
لكن ماذا بوسعها أن تفعل؟
Weep to the magistrate?
هل تبكي أمام القاضي؟
Storm my gates?
اقتحموا أبوابي؟
Curse me?
هل لعنتني؟
Chen Yanyun will have the shop
ستمتلك تشين يانيون المتجر
unsealed soon enough,
سيتم فتحه قريباً بما فيه الكفاية،
but it means nothing.
لكن هذا لا يعني شيئاً.
The whispers don't
الهمسات لا
unseal themselves.
يفتحون أنفسهم.
No husband in the city
لا يوجد زوج في المدينة
will let his wife
سيسمح لزوجته
set foot in a place
ضع قدمك في مكان ما
where men are
حيث يوجد الرجال
rumored to lurk.
يشاع أنه يتربص.
That, my dear,
هذا يا عزيزتي،
is how you
هكذا أنت
ruin someone properly.
أفسد شخصًا ما تمامًا.
Your wisdom has no equal, my lady!
حكمتكِ لا مثيل لها يا سيدتي!
We've been
لقد كنا
lending out heavily of late.
الإقراض بكثافة في الآونة الأخيرة.
The principal is running thin.
المدير بدأ يفقد موارده.
Shall we
هلا فعلنا
add to it?
هل تريد إضافة شيء إليه؟
That much already?
هل هذا كثير بالفعل؟
Since last month,
منذ الشهر الماضي،
a dozen new borrowers.
اثنا عشر مقترضاً جديداً.
Word of mouth
التوصية الشفهية
does wonders,
يصنع العجائب،
and before long,
وقريبًا،
they're all knocking at our door.
جميعهم يطرقون بابنا.
The crown
التاج
grows fat on silver,
يكتسب ثروة من الفضة،
yet the poor
ومع ذلك، فإن الفقراء
remain in want.
يبقى في حاجة.
Add five thousand taels.
أضف خمسة آلاف تيل.
Keep it moving.
استمر في التقدم.
My lady,
سيدتي،
a letter from the Chens.
رسالة من عائلة تشين.
Now what is she scheming?
ما الذي تخطط له الآن؟
She wants to meet in person?
هل ترغب في اللقاء شخصياً؟
Let's see
لنرى
what tricks she's conjured.
يا لها من حيلٍ دبرتها!
I came as you asked.
لقد أتيت كما طلبت.
What do you want?
ماذا تريد؟
I've come to repay a debt.
لقد جئت لأسدد ديناً.
Pardon?
عفو؟
A debt?
دين؟
A few of my staff found themselves
وجد بعض موظفيّ أنفسهم
in dire straits
في وضع حرج
after the shop was sealed.
بعد إغلاق المتجر.
With no wages
بدون أجر
coming in,
عند الدخول،
they had nowhere
لم يكن لديهم مكان
to turn
للتحول
and borrowed from a lender.
واقترض من جهة إقراض.
It turns out…
اتضح أن...
that lender was you.
ذلك المُقرض كنت أنت.
I only learned of it recently.
لم أعرف بذلك إلا مؤخراً.
I've always said
لطالما قلت
that such loans
أن مثل هذه القروض
are nothing but traps
ليست سوى فخاخ
for the desperate.
للمحتاجين.
In total, they borrowed
في المجمل، اقترضوا
a considerable sum.
مبلغ كبير.
What they actually received
ما حصلوا عليه بالفعل
was far less,
كان أقل بكثير،
your usual practice,
ممارستك المعتادة،
I believe.
أعتقد ذلك.
Daily interest,
الفائدة اليومية،
compounded,
مُركّب،
seven days on paper,
سبعة أيام على الورق،
ten days on your ledger.
عشرة أيام في دفتر حساباتك.
Borrow out of desperation,
الاقتراض بدافع اليأس،
and you're risking more than money.
وأنت تخاطر بأكثر من مجرد المال.
So I'd rather settle this today.
لذا أفضل أن أحسم هذا الأمر اليوم.
I haven't the faintest idea
ليس لدي أدنى فكرة
what you mean.
ماذا تقصد.
No?
لا؟
Then perhaps she does.
إذن ربما تفعل ذلك.
I was told she's the one
قيل لي إنها هي
managing the loans.
إدارة القروض.
You were
كنت
acting on her instructions, right?
أليس كذلك؟
Certainly not.
بالتأكيد لا.
A lady of breeding shall not
لا يجوز لسيدة من أصل نبيل أن
make such accusations.
توجيه مثل هذه الاتهامات.
I would never
لن أفعل ذلك أبداً
stoop to such a thing.
أن ينحدر المرء إلى مثل هذا الأمر.
Quite right!
صحيح تماماً!
A lady of your status
سيدة بمكانتك
wouldn't touch something
لن يلمس شيئًا
this beneath her.
هذا لا يليق بها.
So this truly isn't yours?
إذن هذا ليس ملكك حقاً؟
Absolutely none of it.
لا شيء من ذلك على الإطلاق.
Then I'll
ثم سأفعل
take them back.
أعدهم.
Qingpu,
تشينغبو،
spread the word.
انشر الخبر.
Should anyone come to collect,
في حال حضر أي شخص لاستلام الطلب،
send them to me.
أرسلها إليّ.
I'll personally
سأفعل ذلك شخصياً
escort them to the magistrate.
مرافقتهم إلى القاضي.
The penalty for
عقوبة لـ
running illegal loans,
إدارة القروض غير القانونية،
I believe it's a flogging.
أعتقد أنه جلد.
A memorable one!
تجربة لا تُنسى!
Lady Wang,
السيدة وانغ،
until next time.
إلى اللقاء في المرة القادمة.
My lady,
سيدتي،
I had no idea...
لم أكن أعرف...
She arranged
هي التي رتبت الأمر
every one
الجميع
of those clients.
من بين هؤلاء العملاء.
I beg your forgiveness!
أرجو منكم الصفح!
My lady,
سيدتي،
she denied everything.
أنكرت كل شيء.
I knew she would.
كنت أعرف أنها ستفعل ذلك.
I merely
أنا فقط
wished her to know
تمنت أن تعلم
I am not one
أنا لست واحداً منهم
to be trifled with.
لا ينبغي الاستهانة به.
If we truly wish to
إذا كنا نرغب حقًا في
bring her down
أسقطها أرضاً
and revive the shop,
وإعادة إحياء المتجر،
we will need someone's help.
سنحتاج إلى مساعدة شخص ما.
Ms. Qingpu,
السيدة كينغبو،
you with a sword, how rare!
أنت تحمل سيفاً، يا له من أمر نادر!
I train every day.
أتدرب كل يوم.
Full summer and yet
صيف كامل ومع ذلك
there's a chill in the air.
هناك برودة في الجو.
Yeah, um...
أجل، امم...
Come to think of it,
بالتفكير في الأمر،
haven't the winters been getting harsher?
ألم تصبح فصول الشتاء أكثر قسوة؟
And if
وإذا
the capital feels it,
تشعر العاصمة بذلك،
the men
الرجال
on the frontier
على الحدود
must be half-frozen...
يجب أن يكون نصف مجمد...
Those winter coats
تلك المعاطف الشتوية
really cannot wait!
لا أطيق الانتظار حقاً!
Master Ji?
المعلم جي؟
My lady, Master Ji is here!
سيدتي، السيد جي هنا!
I haven't...
ليس لدي...
finished yet...
لم ينتهِ بعد...
Jinzhao!
جينتشاو!
Yao!
لهم!
I wondered
تساءلت
when you'd come.
عندما تأتي.
The moment I arrived, I came to you.
لحظة وصولي، أتيت إليك.
Is he treating you well?
هل يعاملك معاملة حسنة؟
That's all I needed to hear.
هذا كل ما كنت بحاجة لسماعه.
Come, sit.
تعال، اجلس.
Half of the winter coats,
نصف معاطف الشتاء،
packed with
مليء بـ
rotten cotton?
قطن فاسد؟
Yes.
نعم.
That's exactly...
هذا بالضبط...
The Dais
المنصة
used Lord Fu's influence
استغل نفوذ اللورد فو
to claim that contract.
للمطالبة بذلك العقد.
And
و
this is what they delivered.
هذا ما قدموه.
Lady Fu
السيدة فو
will be
سيكون
losing sleep over this.
أعاني من الأرق بسبب هذا الأمر.
That's the reason
هذا هو السبب
I'm here.
أنا هنا.